If you had orange juice with your
breakfast, there is a good chance you
have a Florida farmer to thank.
But right now, the entire state of
Florida is in the middle of its worst
drought in 25 years, and it's
threatening all kinds of crops,
especially the orange crop. Fox's Amy
Gallo joins us live from Bartow,
Florida, and Amy, this is happening in a
state that provides nearly 20% of the
nation's citrus. Good morning to you.
Good morning, Tom. Yeah, that's exactly
right. We provide a good chunk of the
citrus that we consume here in the
United States, and right now extremely
dry conditions across the state of
Florida are leading farmers to have to
water their crops more. That means
they're spending much more money on
irrigation, which can get costly really
quickly. And the issue is this is an
industry that's already been hit hard by
the financial struggles that come with
hurricanes, as well as citrus greening
disease.
Florida citrus is more than just a tasty
snack.
>> It's definitely a lifeline to a lot of
Floridians here. It's It's what they
depend on. But Mother Nature has been
anything but dependable lately. The
hurricanes, the disease,
um,
and now drought.
>> Back in 2000, Florida's citrus industry
covered around 900,000 acres. Now it's
down to just over 200,000, according to
the USDA. It's really It's It's farming
with all the challenges that you have,
but we're looking for a break right now.
Unfortunately, that break might not be
coming anytime soon, because 100% of
Florida is in a drought, the state's
worst dry spell in 25 years. It It's
been challenging, uh, over the last
year. During the bloom period, uh, water
is critical. Uh, it determines how well
the fruit sizes, and ultimately, um, you
know, how large your crop will be.
Inside these white tents, Dundee Citrus
has created a safe haven. Originally
installed to prevent disease in plants,
they're now also helping to manage soil
moisture.
>> Everything is pumped through a series of
pipes into this black tubing and it's um
every tree has a very small emitter that
puts um you know, puts out an amount of
water. It creates the perfect
environment for growing healthy crops,
even in these historically dry
conditions. This 10-acre pod will
produce
um between 8,000 and 10,000 boxes per
pod. The trees in this environment,
they're happy. They grow faster than
trees do in traditional outdoor uh
groves and they come into production
quicker. So, it's it's one way that we
can really get the industry back on
track.
So, you're probably wondering whether
this will affect prices at the store for
things like oranges or grapefruit. And
for right now, the answer is it's not
really affecting it too much. According
to the CEO of Dundee Citrus, prices for
Florida citrus are pretty stable, even
despite the drought and the recent
freezes we had here. Tom.